Guide to the Elizabeth Mayer and Wolfgang Sauerländer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elizabeth Mayer and Wolfgang Sauerländer papers
1933-1977
YCGL MSS 36
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of letters to Elizabeth Mayer and Wolfgang Sauerländer concerning their translation and editorial work, with related reports and legal documents relating to business operations of Pantheon Books, Random House, and the Bollingen Foundation. Many letters concern Mayer's and Sauerländer's personal and professional relationships with Kurt and Helen Wolff. Other correspondence includes letters to Sauerländer from Jacques Schriffrin, letters and documents relating to translations of Bertolt Brecht by Ralph Manheim, and letters to Mayer from Norman Holmes Pearson and Erich and Fine Kahler, accompanied by photographs of Fine Kahler. Most correspondence to Sauerländer includes typescript carbon copies of his responses.
Mayer, Elizabeth
Sauerländer, Wolfgang
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Beate Sauerländer on the Beinecke German Literature Collection Fund, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Elizabeth Mayer (1884-1970)
Elizabeth Mayer (1884-1970), German-American translator.
Wolfgang Sauerländer
Wolfgang Sauerländer, editor, employed by Pantheon Books and the Bollingen Foundation. Sauerländer was married to Beate Sauerländer, daughter of Elizabeth Mayer.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters to Elizabeth Mayer and Wolfgang Sauerländer concerning their translation and editorial work, with related reports and legal documents relating to business operations of Pantheon Books, Random House, and the Bollingen Foundation. Many letters concern Mayer's and Sauerländer's personal and professional relationships with Kurt and Helen Wolff. Other correspondence includes letters to Sauerländer from Jacques Schriffrin, letters and documents relating to translations of Bertolt Brecht by Ralph Manheim, and letters to Mayer from Norman Holmes Pearson and Erich and Fine Kahler, accompanied by photographs of Fine Kahler. Most correspondence to Sauerländer includes typescript carbon copies of his responses.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Letters to Elizabeth Mayer, 1933-1966. II. Wolfgang Sauerländer Correspondence, 1953-1977. III. Other Papers, 1956-1972.
Bollingen series; Authors, German -- 20th Century; Editors -- United States -- Archives; German literature -- 20th Century; German literature -- Translations into English; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Translators -- United States -- Archives; Photographs; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Translators -- United States -- 20th Century; Kahler, Erich, 1885-1970; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956 -- Translations into English; Kahler, Fine; Manheim, Ralph, 1907-1992; Mayer, Elizabeth; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Sauerländer, Wolfgang; Schiffrin, Jacques; Wolff, Helen, 1906-1994; Wolff, Kurt, 1887-1963; Bollingen Foundation; Editorial Noguer; Pantheon Books; Random House (Firm)
- Letters to Elizabeth Mayer, Series I
  - Kahler, Erich and Fine, 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 autograph letter, signed, from Erich Kahler, 1948
    6 typed letters, signed, fom Fine Kahler, 1933-1945, with photographs of Fine Kahler
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1936-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Wolff, Kurt, 1938-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    35 letters, including 1 photocopy, and 5 postcards. Early letters relate to Wolff's experiences in France after fleeing from Italy, his efforts to immigrate, and the political situation. Later letters contain comments about Mayer's collaboration with W. H. Auden.
- Wolfgang Sauerländer Correspondence, Series II
  - Baynes, Cary, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 autograph letters, signed
  - Bollingen Foundation, [1960s] (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    About Sauerländer's employment with the Bollingen Series
  - Cohn, Jules (Box 1, Folder 10)
    With related printed materials
  - Editorial Noguer, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gross, Flora and Gerry, 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Kerringan, Anthony (Box 1, Folder 14)
    3 typed letters, signed
  - Random House, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    About Sauerländer's work for Random House on Ralph Manheim's Brecht translation
  - Schiffrin, Jacques, [1940s] (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Letters and memos, with copies of letters from Sauerländer, about Pantheon Books
  - Wolff, Christian, [1960s] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    1 typed letter, signed, with copies of 3 letters from Sauerländer
  - Wolff, Helen, 1964-[early 1970s] (Box 2, Folder 20)
    6 letters, with copies of many letters from Sauerländer
  - Wolff, Helen, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    24 letters and memos, about indexing and editing done by Sauerländer, with copies of many letters from Sauerländer
  - Wolff, Kurt, 1953-1963 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    18 letters and memos, about Pantheon Books and the Bollingen Series, with clippings and copies of letters from Sauerländer
  - Wolff, Kurt, [mostly 1958] (Box 2, Folder 24)
    11 letters and memos, with copies of letters from Sauerländer
  - Wolff, Kurt, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    32 letters and memos, from Wolff at Locarno, with copies of many letters from Sauerländer, showing how Wolff ran his business from a distance
  - Wolff, Nikolaus, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Other Papers, Series III
  - Bollingen Foundation, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Copy of an agreement between Pantheon Books and the Bollingen Foundation
  - Pantheon Books, 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
    Copy of an account of a European scouting trip by Kurt Wolff, about his visits to authors, artists, and publishers, typescript carbon, 21 pages
  - Random House, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Documents relating to Sauerländer's work as a consultant on the Random House Brecht translation
  - Other printed material (Box 2, Folder 33)